<chapter id="ch-intro">
  <title>Introduction</title>
  
  <!-- ========================================================= -->
  <sect1>
    <title>Speech Synthesizers</title>
    
    
    <!-- ********************************************************* -->
    <sect2>
      <title>Hardware devices</title>
      
      <para>
	Hardware synthesizers are the devices, which may be connected mostly to
	serial port of a PC. Application may send textual data to the port and the device
	converts it to spoken letters and words. Data may contain also several
	control sequences in the form of escaped characters as commands. The problem,
	we are facing, is that each of these devices uses its own communication protocol.

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Apollo</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>...</para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	
      </para>
      
    </sect2>
    
    <!-- ********************************************************* -->
    <sect2>
      <title>MBROLA</title>
      
      <para>
	MBROLA is a software speech synhesis ...
      </para>
    </sect2>
    
    <!-- ********************************************************* -->
    <sect2>
      <title>Mluvitko</title>
      
      <para>
	Mluvitko is a simple (and very light) czech software speech synhesis ...
      </para>
    </sect2>
    
  </sect1>
  
  <!-- ========================================================= -->
  
  <sect1>
    <title>Speaking Applications</title>
    
    <para>
    </para>
    
    <!-- ********************************************************* -->
    <sect2>
      <title>EmacSpeak</title>
      
      <para>The Emacspeak by T. V. Raman &lt;raman@cs.cornell.edu> software package
	provides speech output for Emacs, and includes "speech servers" for
	the DECtalk speech synthesizers.</para>
      
      <para>The package emacspeak-ss provides servers for several additional synthesizers:</para>
      
      <itemizedlist mark="opencircle">
	<listitem><para>DoubleTalk PC and AT from <ulink url="http://www.rcsys.com/">R. C. Systems</ulink></para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Braille 'n Speak, Type 'n Speak, and Braille Lite from <ulink url="http://www.blazie.com">Blazie Engineering</ulink></para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Accent SA</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Apollo 2, JUNO, and JUNO-sp from Dolphin.</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Spanish ciber 232</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Spanish ciber 232 Plus</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Spanish PC Hablado notebook</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      
      <para>None of these programs are normally run by the user directly.  Instead,
	they are run by Emacs. That is: Emacs runs the emacspeak code, which executes
	Tcl, which interprets the server code. This approach is too closely "wired"
	to usage with Emacspeak, so it may not be used for our general purposes.</para>
      
      <para>This does not mean, that these servers are compleetly a bad idea and we
	can not use them. Thanks to the author  <ulink url="mailto:jrv@vanzandt.mv.com">Jim Van Zandt</ulink>), we can learn from
	the sources and write the output driver modules for speechd (emacspeek-ss is
	GPL).</para>
      
      <para>Bart Bunting is working on a speech server using the MBROLA software
	speech synthesizer.</para>
      
    </sect2>
    
    <!-- ********************************************************* -->
    <!--sect2>
      <title>Bash</title>
      
      <para>
      </para>
      
    </sect2-->
    
    <!-- ********************************************************* -->
    <sect2>
      <title>X Window System</title>
      <para>
	There is currently (as far as we know...) no speach support for
	speaking X Window programs. However several windowing toolkit libraries take
	speech support into a focus last few years. These are:

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>wxWindows</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Java AWT</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>FOX toolkit</para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

	We hope to be able to integrate speechd into these projects in the future.

      </para>
    </sect2>
    
  </sect1>
  
</chapter>
